A Guide to the Dorothee Stelzer King Architectural Collection, 1950-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Dorothee Stelzer King Architectural Collection, 1950-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2013-023
3.6 cu. ft.
Born in Berlin, Germany. Dorothee Stelzer King is an architect and professor who has practiced in Germany, the United States, and the Bahamas. The collection consists of material (drawings, presentation boards, photographs, and printed material) created and accumulated by King as a student and during her professional career. Some examples include: her award-winning student project of creating a flexible and transportable exhibition hall and her project work for the Government of the Bahamas. Materials in this collection range in date from 1950-2008.
King, Dorothée
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Dorothee Stelzer King Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in December 2008.
Biographical Note
Born in Berlin, Germany. King is an architect and professor who has practiced in Germany, the United States, and the Bahamas. She graduated from the Hochschule fur Bildende Kunste (HBK) with the title 'Diplom Architect HBK Berlin' in 1962. Upon graduating from HBK she worked for two years (1962-1964) in the architectural office of Dipl. Ing. Hilde Westrom, one of the few independently working women architects in Berlin. King would go on to receive the Airlift Memorial Scholarship and Fulbright Travel Grant allowing her to study under Louis I. Kahn in his Master Studio at the University of Pennsylvania (1965-1967). Her experiences with Kahn would greatly influence her own style of teaching at the Pratt Institute School of Architecture (1969-1981) and other organizations.
King and her husband, fellow architect Douglas King, were offered the opportunity to work as architects with the Government of the Bahamas in Nassau (1981-1985). There she primarily worked on projects for the Ministries of Health and Housing including: public rental units with a senior citizen complex, design for a high school library in Cooperstown, and as project architect and head construction supervisor for the Bahamas Nursing School. 1985-1991 saw King commuting between New York, Nassau, and Florida as she finished supervising the Bahamas Nursing School and partnered with with husband on a design-build company called Kingston Homes in West Palm Beach, Florida. Shortly after returning to New York full-time (1991) King began teaching at several New York institutions and public schools within the city (1993-2008).
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by King during the course of her days as a student and her professional career. This material primarily comprises drawings, presentation boards, photographs, and printed material related to various design projects undertaken by King during the time period 1957 to 1988. Also included within the collection is a detailed biographical narrative written by King describing the trajectory of her career and a family history and genealogy titled From the Basilius, Gersdorff and Horn Families to the King, Kruppa and Stelzer Families, also written by King.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architecture; International Archives of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Personal Papers, 1950-2008
  - Biographical narrative, 2008 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Certificates, Awards, Diplomas, etc., 1950-1976 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Family history and genealogy, From the Basilius, Gersdorff and Horn Families to the King, Kruppa and Stelzer Families, written by Dorothee Stelzer King, 2007 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Photograph, Dorothee S. King, circa 1980 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Scholarships [applications, correspondence, award, and recommendations], 1964 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Student Projects, 1957-1962
    - Austellungbau Variabel-Tranportabel [Exhibition Hall Flexible -Transportable], HDK Berlin, 1962 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 3, Box-folder 1:6)
      Scope and Content
      Materials present include a project description, 2 model photographs, 1 set of photographic reductions of the model, 1 set of slides of the drawings and model, along with a publication "ars viva 62" featuring the project. Drawings include: 7 original ink drawings on board and transparent paper and 2 blueprints.
    - Ferienhaus in Muggelheim [vacation cottage], 1957 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 3)
      2 original ink drawings on board and transparent paper.
    - Reihenhaus [rowhouses], 1958 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 3)
      9 original ink drawings in transparent paper.
    - Trauerhalle/Kapelle [chapel], 1959 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 3)
      7 original ink drawings on transparent paper.
    - Various Projects, HDK Berlin, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Publications: Alliance for Women in Architecture, 1981 and undated (Box-folder 1:8)
- Project Records, 1971-1988
  - Bahamas Nursing School, Nassau, Bahamas, 1983-1988
    - Project description, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Concept sketches, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Contract with the Ministry of Finance, Invoices, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Drawings
      - Blue print copy at 1/4" scale of detailed furniture and equipment layouts for main lecture hall, library, and commons (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 6)
      - Blue print copy at actual drawing size of the architectural drawings: title sheet plus A-1 thru A-35. (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 6)
      - Hand colored blue print copy showing landscaping at actual drawing size of architectural drawing A-1: Site and Location Plan (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 6)
      - Maps and land drawings (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 6)
      - Original presentation drawings - ink on vellum (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 4)
      - Pencil and ink sketches and line drawings used to prepare the final presentation drawings (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 4)
      - Photo-static copies at 1/2 original drawings scale of the architectural drawings A-1 thru A-35 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 1)
    - Landscape, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Material and color samples, light fixture schedule, signage, room finishes, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Memorandums and Correspondence, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Model, study model in chipboard (Box 2)
    - Opening ceremony, June 16, 1987 (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Opening program and press clippings, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Overall program, office management, building program, list of drawings, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Photographs, 1985-1988
      - Negatives, completed building and opening ceremony, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1:18)
      - Negatives, original presentation drawings (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 1)
      - Photographs of completed project, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1:19)
      - Progress photographs (5 folders), January 1986-April 1987 (Box-folder 1:20-24)
  - Cottage on Rose Island, Bahamas, 1988 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 2)
    2 hand colored presentation drawings on prints.
    3 original construction drawings, pencil on vellum.
  - Daylite Apartments Physical Survey and Proposal, Freeport, Grand Bahama, Bahamas, 1980
    - Project report, May 1980 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Library and Administrative Building Coopers Town High School, Abaco, Bahamas, 1983
    - Project description, 1983 (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Drawings: blue print copy at actual drawing size of the architectural drawings: title sheet plus drawings 1-13. (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 5)
    - Drawings: pencil on vellum Drawing 2 showing preliminary plan layout, elevations and sections at 1/8"= 1'-0" (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 2)
  - Townhouse Renovation, King Residence, New York, NY, 1971 (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 2)
    2 hand colored original presentation drawings on board.
  - Sutton Street Public Rental Housing Grants Town Urban Improvement Project, Nassau, Bahamas, 1983
    - Project description, 1983 (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Drawings: blue print copy at actual drawing size of prototype 3 bedroom and 4 bedroom townhouse units -- drawings 1-11. (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 5)
    - Drawings: blue print copy at actual drawings size of Sutton Street Public rental units - site plan and sanitary waste plan. [Note: this project utilizes the prototype 3 and 4 bedroom townhouse units above.] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 5)
    - Drawings: pencil line axonometric drawings on yellow tracing paper and vellum of Sutton Street public rental units (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 11/Folder 2)
    - Nassau, Bahamas Ministry of Housing Specifications, 1983 (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Photographs of completed project, 1983 (Box-folder 1:29)